<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="wlr_layer_shell_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2017 Drew DeVault

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holder not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holder makes no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER
    IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zwlr_layer_shell_v1" version="4">
    <description summary="create surfaces that are layers of the desktop">
      Clients can use this interface to assign the surface_layer role to
      wl_surfaces. Such surfaces are assigned to a "layer" of the output and
      are rendered with a defined z-depth respective to each other. They may
      also be anchored to the edges and corners of a screen and specify
      input handling semantics. This interface should be suitable for
      the implementation of many desktop shell components, and a number of
      flags are provided to assist applications with data such as
      struts, margins, and anchors.
    </description>

    <request name="get_layer_surface">
      <description summary="create a layer_surface from a surface">
        Create a layer surface for an existing surface. This assigns the role
        of layer_surface, or raises a protocol error if another role is
        already assigned.

        Creating a layer surface from a wl_surface which has a buffer attached
        or committed is a client error, and any attempts by a client to attach
        or manipulate a buffer prior to the first layer_surface.configure call
        must also be treated as errors.

        You may pass NULL for output to allow the compositor to decide which
        output to use. Generally this will be the one that the user most
        recently interacted with.

        Clients can specify a namespace that defines the purpose of the layer
        surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwlr_layer_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output" allow-null="true"/>
      <arg name="layer" type="uint" enum="layer" summary="layer to add this surface to"/>
      <arg name="namespace" type="string" summary="namespace for the layer surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="role" value="0" summary="wl_surface has another role"/>
      <entry name="invalid_layer" value="1" summary="layer value is invalid"/>
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="2" summary="wl_surface has a buffer attached or committed"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="layer">
      <entry name="background" value="0" summary="the background layer"/>
      <entry name="bottom" value="1" summary="the bottom layer"/>
      <entry name="top" value="2" summary="the top layer"/>
      <entry name="overlay" value="3" summary="the overlay layer"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor" since="3">
      <description summary="destroy the layer_shell object">
        This request indicates that the client will not use the layer_shell
        object any more. Objects that have been created through this instance
        are not affected.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwlr_layer_surface_v1" version="4">
    <description summary="layer metadata interface">
      An interface that may be implemented by a wl_surface, for surfaces that
      are designed to be rendered as a layer of a stacked desktop-like
      environment.

      Layer surface state (layer, size, anchor, exclusive zone, keyboard
      interactivity) is double-buffered, and will be applied at the time
      wl_surface.commit of the corresponding wl_surface is called.

      Attaching a null buffer to a layer surface unmaps it.

      Unmapping a layer_surface of the currently focused window will result
      in the layer_surface losing focus. The compositor should then focus
      another surface.

      The client must set an anchor of at least one, or set the size to a
      non-zero width and height, otherwise the compositor will raise a
      bad_anchor error.
    </description>

    <request name="set_size">
      <description summary="sets the size of the surface">
        Sets the size of the surface in surface-local coordinates. The
        compositor will display the surface with the given size and may
        ignore its buffer contents; the compositor may choose to force the
        surface to be larger or smaller than the requested size.

        If you pass 0 for either value, the compositor will assign it and
        inform you of the assignment in the configure event. You must set your
        anchor to opposite edges in the axis the compositor is determining the
        size of and not include a margin in the axis the compositor is
        determining the size of, or else the request will fail and the
        compositor will raise a protocol error.

        The width and height arguments are in surface-local coordinates.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_anchor">
      <description summary="configures the anchor point of the surface">
        Requests that the compositor anchor the surface to the specified
        edges and corners. If two opposite edges are specified, the
        compositor will spread the surface in between.

        On compositors implementing xdg-output, if two opposite edges of the
        compositor's output are specified, the compositor will cover the full
        surface of the output's work area.

        The edges and corners are described by the anchor enum. All anchor
        values are valid.
      </description>
      <arg name="anchor" type="uint" enum="anchor"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_exclusive_zone">
      <description summary="configures the exclusive geometry of this surface">
        Requests that the compositor avoids occluding an area with other
        surfaces. The compositor's use of this information is
        implementation-dependent - do not assume that this region will not
        actually be occluded.

        A positive value is only meaningful if the surface is anchored to one
        edge or an edge and both perpendicular edges. If the surface is not
        anchored, anchored to more than one edge (not including perpendicular
        edges), or anchored to a perpendicular edge, the exclusive_zone is
        ignored.

        The exclusive_zone is calculated from the edge that the surface is
        anchored to. If the surface is anchored to the top edge, the
        exclusive_zone is the distance from the top edge to the top of the
        surface. If the surface is anchored to the bottom edge, the
        exclusive_zone is the distance from the bottom of the surface to the
        bottom edge.

        Setting the exclusive_zone to -1 indicates that the layer surface
        does not wish to move or resize to accommodate for other surfaces,
        and hints that the exclusive_zone should not be taken into account
        for the surface. This is useful when the surface wants to take the
        full space of the screen.

        If the compositor respects requests for arbitrary values of the
        exclusive_zone, the compositor will place new layer surfaces
        respecting the most recently requested exclusive_zone.
      </description>
      <arg name="zone" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_margin">
      <description summary="sets a margin from the anchor point">
        Requests that the surface be placed some distance away from the anchor
        point on the output, in surface-local coordinates. Setting this value
        for edges you are not anchored to has no effect.

        The exclusive_zone includes the margin for the relevant edge.
      </description>
      <arg name="top" type="int"/>
      <arg name="right" type="int"/>
      <arg name="bottom" type="int"/>
      <arg name="left" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_keyboard_interactivity">
      <description summary="requests keyboard events">
        Set how keyboard events are delivered to this surface. By default,
        layer shell surfaces do not receive keyboard events; this request can
        be used to enable delivery of keyboard events to a surface.

        Keyboard events from existing or new input devices will be delivered
        normally. Other clients will not receive keyboard events while this
        surface has focus, as per normal Wayland semantics.

        Advisory: it is discouraged to set this value to anything other than
        none for desktop backgrounds, dock or status bars, notification feeds,
        and similar layer shell use cases. These surfaces usually do not need
        to receive keyboard input and should not be stealing it from other
        clients.

        This setting is inherited by child surfaces set by the get_popup
        request.

        Layer surfaces receive pointer, touch, and tablet events normally. If
        you do not want to receive them, set the input region on your surface
        to an empty region.

        Clients that do not set the interactivity to none may be moved by the
        compositor above the keyboard focus surface. This is compositor-
        specific behavior.
      </description>
      <arg name="keyboard_interactivity" type="uint" enum="keyboard_interactivity"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_popup">
      <description summary="assign this layer_surface as an xdg_popup parent">
        This assigns an xdg_popup's parent to this layer_surface.  This popup
        should have been created via xdg_surface::get_popup with the parent set
        to NULL, and this request must be invoked before committing the popup's
        initial state.

        See the documentation of xdg_popup for more details about what an
        xdg_popup is and how it is used.
      </description>
      <arg name="popup" type="object" interface="xdg_popup"/>
    </request>

    <request name="ack_configure">
      <description summary="ack a configure event">
        When a configure event is received, if a client commits the
        surface in response to the configure event, then the client
        must make an ack_configure request sometime before the commit
        request, passing along the serial of the configure event.

        If the client receives multiple configure events before it
        can respond to one, it only has to ack the last configure event.

        A client is not required to commit immediately after sending
        an ack_configure request - it may even ack_configure several times
        before its next surface commit.

        A client may send multiple ack_configure requests before committing,
        but only the last request sent before a commit indicates which configure
        event the client really is responding to.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial from the configure event"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the layer_surface">
        This request destroys the layer surface.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="suggest a surface change">
        The configure event asks the client to resize its surface.

        Clients should arrange their surface for the new states, and then send
        an ack_configure request with the serial sent in this configure event at
        some point before committing the new surface.

        The client is free to dismiss all but the last configure event it
        received.

        The width and height arguments specify the size of the window in
        surface-local coordinates.

        The size is a hint, in the sense that the client is free to ignore it if
        it doesn't resize, pick a smaller size (to satisfy aspect ratio or
        resize in steps of NxM pixels). If the client picks a smaller size and
        is anchored to two opposite edges (i.e. is in a mode that would
        normally result in the surface being bigger than the hint from the
        configure event), the compositor can place the layer surface
        anywhere it likes. In addition, vertical anchors imply horizontal
        stretching (after accounting for margins), and horizontal anchors
        imply vertical stretching. Only when combined do both axes get
        stretched.

        The compositor can send configure events at any time, even before the
        first attach. The surface is initially unmapped until the first
        ack_configure is sent and a buffer is attached.

        The width and height are in surface local coordinates and are never
        zero at the same time.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint"/>
    </event>

    <event name="closed">
      <description summary="surface should be closed">
        The closed event is sent by the compositor when the surface will no
        longer be shown. The output may have been destroyed or the user may
        have asked for it to be removed. Further changes to the surface will
        be ignored. The client should destroy the resource after receiving
        this event, and create a new surface if they so choose.
      </description>
    </event>

    <enum name="keyboard_interactivity">
      <entry name="none" value="0">
        <description summary="no keyboard focus is possible">
          This value indicates that this surface is not interested in keyboard
          events and the compositor should never assign it the keyboard focus.

          This is the default value, set for newly created layer shell surfaces.

          This is useful for e.g. desktop widgets that display information or
          only have interaction mechanisms that are not the keyboard.
        </description>
      </entry>
      <entry name="exclusive" value="1">
        <description summary="request exclusive keyboard focus">
          Request exclusive keyboard focus if this surface is above the shell
          surface layer.

          For the top and overlay layers, the seat will always give exclusive
          keyboard focus to the top-most layer which has keyboard interactivity
          set to exclusive. If this layer contains multiple surfaces with
          keyboard interactivity set to exclusive, the compositor determines
          the one receiving the keyboard focus in an implementation-defined
          manner. In this case, no guarantee is made when this surface will
          receive keyboard focus, if ever.

          For the bottom and background layers, the compositor is allowed to
          use normal focus semantics.

          This setting is mainly intended for applications that need to ensure
          they receive all keyboard events, such as a lock screen or a password
          prompt.
        </description>
      </entry>
      <entry name="on_demand" value="2" since="4">
        <description summary="request keyboard focus on demand">
          This requests the compositor to allow this surface to be focused and
          unfocused by the user in an implementation-defined manner. The user
          must be able to unfocus this surface.
        </description>
      </entry>
    </enum>

    <enum name="anchor" bitfield="true">
      <entry name="top" value="1" summary="the top edge of the anchor rectangle"/>
      <entry name="bottom" value="2" summary="the bottom edge of the anchor rectangle"/>
      <entry name="left" value="4" summary="the left edge of the anchor rectangle"/>
      <entry name="right" value="8" summary="the right edge of the anchor rectangle"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_surface_state" value="0" summary="provided surface state is invalid"/>
      <entry name="invalid_size" value="1" summary="size is invalid"/>
      <entry name="invalid_anchor" value="2" summary="anchor bitfield is invalid"/>
      <entry name="keyboard_interactivity" value="3" summary="keyboard interactivity is invalid"/>
      <entry name="layer" value="4" summary="layer is invalid"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
